Solving equations with variable on both sides is an important skill in algebra.
Many problems later in the course have this as a part of their solution.
This video will cover the genera strategy for solving these types of equations.
Then, we will go through two examples.
Here is the general procedure.
Pick one side of the equation to be for the constants.
I like to pick the side with the largest coefficient of the variable.
Collect the variable terms on one side by adding or subtracting to both sides.
Afterward, collect the constant terms on the other side.
Finally, multiply or divide both sides by the same number
so that the coefficient of the variable is 1.
Don't forget to check your answer.
Let's do two examples.
Both are very common equations to solve.
Solve the equation.
12 q - 5 = 9q - 20.
I'm going to rewrite the equation.
We'll collect the variable terms on the left because 12 is larger than 9.
Subtract 9q from both sides.
The new equation is 3q - 5 = -20.
Next, add 5 to both sides to get the constants on the right.
Now, the equation is 3q = - 15.
Finally, divide both sides by 3.
The solution is q = -5.
Here is the work to check.
Be careful with the negative numbers in the arithmetic.
This second equation is just like the first.
8c + 7 = -3c - 37.
I'm going to copy the equation.
We'll collect the variable terms on the left because 8 is bigger than -3.
Start by adding 3c to both sides.
We're adding to cancel out the -3c.
The new version of the equation is 11c + 7 = -37.
Subtract 7 from both sides.
11c = -44 is the next version of the equation.
Divide both sides by 11.
The solution is c = -4.
Here is the work to check the equation.
There are lots of negative numbers, so be careful.