Compound interest is more common
than simple interest in banking.
This video will cover compound interest.
Many of the terms are the same between simple interest
and compound interest.
The main difference will be in the formulas.
We will cover the compound interest formula.
Then, we will do some examples.
I will include calculator steps too.
Let's start with the compound interest formula.
With compound interest,
the interest is added to the principal at regular intervals.
We calculate the interest with the updated principal each time.
The time between adding interest to the principal
is called a compounding period.
Here is the compound interest formula.
The variables are very similar to the simple interest formula.
The new variable is the compounding periods per year.
For most problems, there is monthly or quarterly compounding.
Monthly compounding means n = 12.
Quarterly compounding means n = 4.
There is an exponent in this problem.
You will need to use a calculator to do the exponent.
These problems will seem hard at first.
Go one step at a time and they will be easier than they look.
Let's do two examples.
For this first example:
The present value is $5,000.
The annual interest rate is 0.038 as a decimal.
Time is 5 years.
Monthly compounding means n =12.
Start by substituting the values into the formula.
Don't try to simplify anything right now.
5 times 12 is 60.
Inside the parentheses simplifies to 1.003167.
I am writing six decimal places,
but keeping the work in the calculator.
You'll see the steps in a moment.
Next, raise 1.003167 to the 60th power.
The exponent button is the symbol that looks like an up arrow.
Finally, multiply 1.20887 by 5000.
The future value is $6,044.43.
Here are the calculator steps on the Google Calculator app. The exponent button is to the left of 1 and 4.
This last problem is just like the first.
The present value is $18,500.
The annual interest rate is 6.25%
Time is 17 years.
Compounding is quarterly.
That means n = 4.
Start by substituting the numbers into the formula.
Multiply 4 times 17 to get 68.
Inside the parentheses simplifies to 1.015625.
Raise 1.015625 to the 68th power.
to get 2.86992.
Lastly, multiply 18500 and 2.86992.
The future value is $53,093.55.
Here are the calculator steps for this problem.