This is our second video about compound interest.
We will work the problems from the last video backwards.
This video will cover:
The present value formula for compound interest.
Then we'll do three problems.
I'll show the solutions on a calculator.
First, a few reminders.
The present value of an account or investment is the value now.
The future value of an account or investment
is the value in a given time in the future.
The reason we want to calculate present value is to know
how much money we need now to reach a future goal.
We can use the rest of our money for other things.
For example, if you need $20,000 to buy a car
five years from now, how much do we need to invest today?
First, we'll look at the present value formula
using compound interest.
Here is the formula.
The bottom of the fraction is exactly the calculation
we did with future value.
The difference is that we're dividing by the number
instead of multiplying.
The best way to do the division in a calculator
is to use the calculator's memory function.
Let's go through some examples.
In the first example:
Future value is $250,000.
Annual interest rate is 0.0345 as a decimal.
Time is 25 years.
Annual compounding means n equals 1.
First, substitute the values into the equation.
Don't try to simplify at this step.
Multiply 1 times 25 to get an exponent of 25.
The part in the parentheses simplifies to 1.0345.
After taking the exponent,
the bottom of the fraction is 2.334868.
Finally, after doing the division,
we get $107,072.43 for the present value.
This means we more than double our money over 25 years.
Here is the calculation on the Google Calculator app.
For this step, use the history to copy and paste the old number.
For this problem:
Future value is $150,000.
Annual interest rate is 0.0481 as a decimal.
Time is 35 years.
Quarterly compounding means n equals 4.
First, substitute the values into the equation.
Multiply 4 times 35 to get an exponent of 140.
The part in the parentheses simplifies to 1.012025.
Doing the exponent,
the bottom of the fraction becomes 5.330571.
Perform the division to get $28,139.58 for the present value.
The future value is more than five times the starting money.
The calculator steps are the same as the last problem.
This is the last problem:
Future value is $150,000.
Annual interest rate is 0.0481 as a decimal.
Time is 35 years.
Monthly compounding means n equals 12.
This is almost the same as the last problem.
The number of compounding periods is different.
First, substitute the values into the equation.
Multiply 12 times 35 to get an exponent of 420.
The parentheses simplifies to 1.004008.
Doing the exponent,
the bottom of the fraction becomes 5.366280.
Perform the division to get $27,952.33 for the present value.
More after this.
The present value is lower
in this problem than in the last problem.
That is because with more compounding periods,
the money grows a little faster.
So, you can start with less and end with the same amount.