There are several layers to the order of operations.
Now that we’ve looked at some order of operations problems,
let’s try some that are a bit more involved.
This video will do a quick review of the order of operations.
Then, we’ll work two examples.
We covered the order of operations in greater detail.
For this video, we’ll do a short review.
When you simplify an expression, work in the following steps.
Parentheses first, working inside to outside.
Second, do all exponents.
The third level is to do all multiplications and divisions.
Do them at the same time, working left to right.
Finally, perform all additions and subtractions.
Again, do them at the same time, working left to right.
Let’s work through two examples.
The first example is 3 times parentheses 1 plus 9 times 6 then minus 4 squared.
First we work inside the parentheses.
The first operation to do inside the parentheses is 9 times 6, which is 54.
The second operation inside the parentheses is 1 plus 54.
The parentheses simplifies to 55.
We’re done with the parentheses.
Next up is exponents.
4 squared is 16
We’re done with exponents.
The next operation is multiplication.
3 times 55 is 165.
Finally, we subtract.
165 minus 16 is 149.
The final answer is 149.
The next example has brackets and parentheses.
Work inside to outside.
We want to simplify 2 bracket 1 plus 3 times parentheses 10 minus 2.
Subtract inside the parentheses.
10 minus 2 is 8
Inside the brackets, do the multiplication first.
3 times 8 is 24.
To finish inside the brackets, add 1 and 24.
The brackets simplify to be 25.
We’ve done all the grouping symbols.
Also, there are no exponents in the problem.
There is one multiplication left.
2 times 25 is 50.
There are no additions or subtractions left either.
The final answer is 50.